<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Games on Jean-Christophe Ploquin &amp; Arthur Gyl: two faces of an artist</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/categories/games/</link><description>Recent content in Games on Jean-Christophe Ploquin &amp; Arthur Gyl: two faces of an artist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/categories/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Acousmatic Music in Video Games</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/acousmatic-music-in-video-games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/acousmatic-music-in-video-games/</guid><description>Long confined to concert halls and artistic installations, acousmatic music today finds an unexpected field of expression: video games. This encounter between electroacoustic tradition and digital interactivity opens fascinating perspectives for contemporary sound art.
When the Invisible Becomes Playable Acousmatic music, the art of pure listening freed from visual sources, shares a fundamental characteristic with video games: the creation of imaginary universes through sound. In my interactive works, this approach allows listeners to discover the richness of electroacoustic composition through an immersive artistic experience.</description></item><item><title>How Music Adapts to Your Genealogy in Ascendance</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/how-music-adapts-to-your-genealogy-in-ascendance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 14:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/how-music-adapts-to-your-genealogy-in-ascendance/</guid><description>Since the launch of Ascendance a few weeks ago, one question keeps coming up: how can music really adapt to a genealogy? Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the behind-the-scenes of this interactive musical innovation.
What is a GEDCOM file? Before exploring the musical magic of Ascendance, let&amp;rsquo;s first understand what makes this experience possible: the GEDCOM file.
GEDCOM (Genealogical Data Communication) is the standard format for genealogy files. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple text file with the .</description></item></channel></rss>