<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Music on Jean-Christophe Ploquin &amp; Arthur Gyl: two faces of an artist</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/categories/music/</link><description>Recent content in Music on Jean-Christophe Ploquin &amp; Arthur Gyl: two faces of an artist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 15:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/categories/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Behind the Scenes: Creating Ascendance</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/behind-the-scenes-creating-ascendance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 15:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/behind-the-scenes-creating-ascendance/</guid><description>Three weeks after the launch of Ascendance, it&amp;rsquo;s time to lift the veil on the behind-the-scenes of this creation. How do you transform an artistic idea into an interactive work? A look back at a creative process that blends electroacoustic composition and software development.
The Creative Spark: When Genealogy Meets Acousmatic Music The idea for Ascendance was born from a simple observation: our family trees resemble musical scores. Each branch evokes a melodic line, each generation suggests a tessitura, each ancestor carries within them a unique sonic story.</description></item><item><title>Acousmatic Music in Video Games</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/acousmatic-music-in-video-games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/acousmatic-music-in-video-games/</guid><description>Long confined to concert halls and artistic installations, acousmatic music today finds an unexpected field of expression: video games. This encounter between electroacoustic tradition and digital interactivity opens fascinating perspectives for contemporary sound art.
When the Invisible Becomes Playable Acousmatic music, the art of pure listening freed from visual sources, shares a fundamental characteristic with video games: the creation of imaginary universes through sound. In my interactive works, this approach allows listeners to discover the richness of electroacoustic composition through an immersive artistic experience.</description></item><item><title>How Music Adapts to Your Genealogy in Ascendance</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/how-music-adapts-to-your-genealogy-in-ascendance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 14:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/how-music-adapts-to-your-genealogy-in-ascendance/</guid><description>Since the launch of Ascendance a few weeks ago, one question keeps coming up: how can music really adapt to a genealogy? Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the behind-the-scenes of this interactive musical innovation.
What is a GEDCOM file? Before exploring the musical magic of Ascendance, let&amp;rsquo;s first understand what makes this experience possible: the GEDCOM file.
GEDCOM (Genealogical Data Communication) is the standard format for genealogy files. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple text file with the .</description></item><item><title>What is Acousmatic Music?</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/what-is-acousmatic-music/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/what-is-acousmatic-music/</guid><description>Acousmatic music remains one of the most mysterious and fascinating currents in contemporary sound creation. But what lies behind this enigmatic term?
The Art of Blind Listening The term &amp;ldquo;acousmatic&amp;rdquo; has its roots in ancient Greece. Pythagoras taught his disciples hidden behind a curtain, deliberately depriving them of any visual information to focus their attention solely on speech. This &amp;ldquo;blind&amp;rdquo; listening allowed for a deeper understanding of the message.
Pierre Schaeffer, pioneer of musique concrète in the 1940s, revived this concept to define a revolutionary musical art: Acousmatic listening invites us to discover sounds for themselves, freed from their origin.</description></item><item><title>My Journey Toward Musical Interactivity</title><link>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/my-journey-toward-musical-interactivity/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 07:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://jcploquin.free.fr/en/blog/my-journey-toward-musical-interactivity/</guid><description>My path toward creating interactive musical works hasn&amp;rsquo;t been a straight line. Between guitar, electroacoustic music, and digital technology, it&amp;rsquo;s a journey made of determining encounters and sometimes unexpected discoveries that led me to explore these new artistic territories.
The Determining Influence of Francis Faber Francis Faber, my former teacher, planted the first seeds of my fascination with interactive art through his installation &amp;ldquo;Totem&amp;rdquo;. This revolutionary work made me understand that music could transcend the traditional concert framework to become an immersive and participatory experience.</description></item></channel></rss>